<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apology for Mr. Walker fully vindicated in a conflict with the author of the Reflections on the Apology. The Reflector's intellectual endowments, learning, and morals display'd. This paper, having waited above three months for the true narrative of the siege of Derry, is now publisht, chiefly, for the diversion of such as have read the Apology.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3545A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133463</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2416:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Apology for Mr. Walker fully vindicated in a conflict with the author of the Reflections on the Apology. The Reflector's intellectual endowments, learning, and morals display'd. This paper, having waited above three months for the true narrative of the siege of Derry, is now publisht, chiefly, for the diversion of such as have read the Apology.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In response to "Reflections on a paper, pretending to be an apology for the failures charged on Mr. Walker's account of the siege of London-Derry.", which in turn is in response to "An apology for the failures charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's printed account of the late siege of Derry", a pretended defence of George Walkers "A true account of the siege of London-Derry.".</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, George, 1645?-1690. --  True account of the siege of London-Derry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apology for the failures charg'd on the Reverend Mr. George Walker's printed account of the late siege of Derry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reflections on a paper, pretending to be an apology for the failures charged on Mr. Walker's account of the siege of London-Derry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Londonderry (Northern Ireland) --  History --  Siege, 1688-1689 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:133463:1"/>
            <p>Apology for Mr. Walker FULLY VINDICATED, In a Conflict with the Author of the Reflections on the <hi>APOLOGY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reflector's Intellectual Endowments, Learning, and Morals diſplay'd.</p>
            <p>This Paper, having waited above three Months for the true Narrative of the Siege of <hi>Derry,</hi> is now publiſht, chiefly, for the <hi>Diverſion</hi> of ſuch as have read the Apology.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid mihi <hi>Londini?</hi> mentiri neſcio, liber,</l>
               <l>Si malus eſt, nequeo laudare, &amp; poſcere,</l>
               <bibl>—<hi>Juv. Sat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>The INTRODUCTION to the Apologiſt's Conflict with the Reflector.</head>
            <p>'TIS expedient the Reader underſtand, That the Pamphlet, bearing the Title of, <hi>Obſervations on Mr.</hi> Walker<hi>'s Account of the Siege of</hi> Derry; this I am now to Examine; and that Sheet Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication, are all three the Births of the ſame Brain, level'd at the ſame (general) ſcope, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by the ſame Genius, deliver'd in the ſame Strain and Style. In thoſe Obſervations are as many obſervable Paſſages as Periods, in ſpecial, two, which, for the courage of an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator, may vie with Sir <hi>Roger</hi> himſelf. One is the Harangue he beſtows chiefly on Mr. <hi>Os. p. 6, 7, 8.</hi> This has run the Gaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let in Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication, and ſo I wave it. The other is in <hi>p. 5.</hi> where the Obſervator celebrates His Majeſty's Bounty to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> in theſe words; — <hi>And howſoever the Sum (I ſuppoſe of 5000.</hi> 
               <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>may bear the ſhew of a Reward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate to his</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Mr.</hi> Walker<hi>'s Service; I dare aver, it is far ſhort of his very Sufferings, and will not reach to the refunding of what he has loſt in his Houſes and Perſonal Eſtate, by Fire, Plunder, and other Outrages done by his and our implacable Enemies.</hi> I quote theſe Paſſages to move the Reader to condole at leaſt, my pitiable Fate, in being ſo unequally match'd with a Champion, of whoſe invincible Proweſs theſe two freſh inſtances are alone a ſufficient demonſtration: Do therefore expect my Judges will do me the Juſtice, <hi>Minos,</hi> ſitting on the Infernal Bench, did <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that they paſs the Apologiſt for a Man, and of ſome Metal too, tho' he ſhould be foil'd (which <hi>Hercules</hi> forbid) by a Combatant, whoſe bare averment will paſs <hi>500 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> or a much ſmaller Sum, for greater weight and value than <hi>5000</hi> 
               <abbr>l.</abbr> of the beſt Coin in our King's Exchequer; and with a few ſquirts of his Pen can make whole Legions of pragmatical, perverſe, murmuring<note n="*" place="margin">Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 6.</note>, malignant Spirits ſcut it away to the Boreal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, faſter than <hi>Tobit</hi>'s Powder could the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly Hobgoblins to their inviſible Cells. But adieu, Elfs and Hobgoblins, Narrators and Vindicators, I'm reſolv'd I'le have one bruſh with Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s late <hi>Lyncean</hi> Obſervator (now contemptuous Reflector, and again, the <hi>Greek</hi> Calends, the Church and States Champion and Orator.) Come ye Sons of <hi>Mars,</hi> behold ſuch a bloody Duel between the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Apologiſt, as <hi>Homer,</hi> till he loſt his Eyes, never ſaw between Mice and Frogs, the <hi>Thracian</hi> Cranes and <hi>Indian</hi> Pigmies. The Reflector indeed makes his approaches ſomewhat Comically, but you may in fine perhaps ſee his Tragical Caſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. After his little Skirmiſh with the Legions before mention'd, he tells you, he had a great Conflict with himſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> between his Will and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; whether he ſhould think firſt, and then ſcribble; or ſcribble firſt, and think after; but his Will being too ſtrong for his Reaſon, ſets him on ſcribling an hour, ay, a week, Learned Animadverſions on the Apology for Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi> And did he not ſcribble to good purpoſe? Yes, ſurely; for 'tis, ſays he, a trifling Pamphlet, an immethodical Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſody, of Vapour, Banter, Fallacy, Equivocations, idle, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, incoherent ſtuff, the ſtyle flat and ruſtick — a thing that deſerves no Conſideration, needs no Anſwer. Thus in his firſt Paragraph he gives his Opinion of the Apology: On the Apologiſt he beſtows the gentile Epithets and Appellations of rude, irrational, ſpiteful, phlegmatick, Hypocrite, ſnarler, invidious, malicious Querent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in his Concluſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends to him <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s Reſolution, <hi>i. e.</hi> to hang himſelf<note n="*" place="margin">Vide the laſt Period in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections.</note>. Theſe are the Embroideries of this Maſter-piece of the Reflector's Art. I had thought Biſhop <hi>Montague,</hi> Mr. (ſince Dean) <hi>Pierce,</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and to name no more, Dr. <hi>Parker,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> all pretending themſelves Champions for our Church, as this Gentleman does, had ſo much prejudic'd their own, ſo much advantag'd their Adverſaries Cauſe by this illiberal Method of managing Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, that no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant would ever write after their Copy. The Equity of that Cauſe is juſtly ſuſpected, which can only be defended by that Rhetorick which is peculiar to the
<pb facs="tcp:133463:2"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecific diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce from the different qualities of the Perſon concern'd for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt it. But to return to our Reflector; one of our Club parted a Queſtion concerning him, Whether 'twas his malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Star, or his evil Genius, put him upon turmoyling as hard as <hi>Siſyphus</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olling the Stone up-hill in Hell; and to as little purpoſe, in anſwering a Pamphlet, of which himſelf had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd, it is a <hi>Thing</hi> (a nothing) deſerves no Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, needs no Anſwer? Another reply'd, There was no need of aſſigning ſo ſenſible an action to Cauſes ſo very remote, and unſeen; that the Animal part proving too hard for the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, or (as he leſs civilly expreſt it.) the Horſe for the Rider, has often produc'd Effects more repugnant to Reaſon, than his Scribling could appear to be to the Reflector's Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination in that Conflict with himſelf whereof this is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentous iſſue. A Second would have it, that his Credit was extreamly ſunk by thoſe before-mentioned, unhappily miſadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd Obſervations, by which Mr. <hi>Wr</hi>'s Favour was like to turn into a laſting feud; that the only way to retrieve both, was to blaſt the Credit of the Apology, as it had done that Account, call'd Mr. <hi>Wr</hi>'s. A Third affirm'd this End not to be the End really deſign'd by the Reflector, who never eſſays directly to confute, on the contrary, ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the Apology: And as oft as he ſtumbles on any truth of a manly Complexion, which ſometimes happens in his Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, improves it in favour of the Apologiſt; but whenever he catches any thing of a contrary Genius (in which he has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Succeſs) he indeed makes it ſimper, or as himſelf has it, caſt a tacit glance on Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> but in fine, renders it the Apologiſts faithful Servant. But I, who will be ſure ever hereafter to help the Reflector at a dead lift, gravely admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd them of their inadvertency, told 'em he had given the Reaſons of his Scribling in his firſt Paragraph, where he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly proteſts, 'twas becauſe he would interpoſe for the Honour of the King, Council, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo rudely, maliciouſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> treated by the Apologiſt. A Fourth roundly averr'd, whatever So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity there might be in the Reflector's Proteſtation, there was not one grain weight of Sincerity in the Proteſtor, or Truth in the Proteſtation; ſince his loſt Labour is beſtow'd to ſupport the tottering Credit of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Narrative, and as all that read not the Apology with a diſloyal Eye, own the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt's Ardent Zeal for the Honour and Intereſt of the King and Government, ſo the Reflector himſelf acquits him of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Crime of Diſloyalty, though it coſt the Reflector very dear, no leſs than the reverſe in fine, of the principal part of what he ſo Solemnly proteſted in front; that therefore the true Reaſon was, the Panic but juſt fear that ſeized the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, that as Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> for his ſuppos'd good Service, had receiv'd the thanks of the Honourable Houſe of Commons now ſitting, ſo his Obſervator might receive upon his Marrow-bones the Reprimand of the ſame Houſe, if no ſeverer Puniſhment, for his very rude, moſt irrational Reflection on His Majeſty's Princely, unparallel'd Bounty to Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> that every good Subject would applaud the Juſtice done to the one, as the Honour done to the other; that there is an inſtance of ſuch Juſtice, of about Ten Years date, where the Crime was not attended with the Tith of the aggravating Circumſtances that ſurround this of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſingular Exploit muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſpecious Character of his ſingular Loyalty, and profo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Concern for the Honour of the King and Government, which might once more place him <hi>rectus in Curia;</hi> and the Apology appearing a few weeks after his Obſervations, he lifts up his Eyes, adores his Propitious Star, by whoſe Benign influx he hopes to be reliev'd ſoon from his anxious Fears, and imminent Perils. What! an Apology for Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s failures; all Reaſon in the World Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Apologiſt ſhould bear the chief part of the Miſpriſons, Miſdemeanors, Falſhoods, Fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, Failures charg'd on Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Obſervator too; for he can better bear both, than the poor Obſervator can bear ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now, I confeſs I find in my ſelf a greater propenſion to pity than proſecute him in his Diſtreſs, ſince I find him as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous (when he deſcends to particular Articles) in acquitting me, as he was temerarious (in his general Charge) in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching me of thoſe Crimes whereof he knew me to be purely innocent. A Fifth bid me conſider, that Charity begins at home; and that I muſt firſt purge my ſelf, then pity my Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; that the Reflector had obſerv'd <hi>Machiavel</hi>'s Maxim, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniare fortiter;</hi> that my ſilence to ſo high an Impeachment of no body knows what, againſt my Soverain, would be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted a tacit Confeſſion of Guilt; that if the Charge were true, the Apologiſt deſerv'd no Vulgar Chaſtiſement; but if falſe (which he did not doubt of) and the Reflector being conſcious of it, deſerv'd the Puniſhment due to ſuch Crimes: Yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd me to acquieſce in that in ſomewhat a diſparallel Caſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by <hi>Apollo</hi> on <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> (which he was ſure would prove the leaſt of the Reflector's Doom,) <hi>i. e.</hi> never to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited when he avouches truth, who ſo ſtrenuouſly avers and proteſts what he knows, and in fine, declares to be a — Mean while (ſays the Gentleman) the Apologiſt's preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince is, to Vindicate the Apology from the imputation of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, and himſelf from the charge of Miſdemeanor towards the Government, both which will be abundantly perform'd by directing the Reader to thoſe paſſages in the Apology which the Reflector pretends to Animadvert upon; and to explain, not the Text, but the Reflector's Comment upon it. I confeſs this Gentleman's ſentiments are ſo much my own on this Subject, that I am reſolv'd to follow Religiouſly his Directions, having firſt declar'd (for I'le have a care of bold Averments, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proteſtations, except againſt the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Popery, Presbytery, and all other deadly ſin) that I would not have drawn my Dagger at this time upon the naked Reflector, if he had not charg'd me with High Miſdemeanors towards my Sacred Soveraign and the Government; Crimes I more deteſt than any I have now proteſted againſt, the Solemn League it ſelf not excepted; ſhall therefore purge my ſelf of 'em, and in this Paper Preſent the Reflector with a Doſe of the Pills I have taken, which if it ſcour not all his three Ventricles, and the Gun-Room too, I ſhall conclude him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted with that Malady, which nothing but the Hellebore of <hi>Anticyra</hi> effectually Cures. And now begging Pardon for the brevity of this Preamble, I'le ſtrenuouſly to't, martially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd never to put up my Sword, till I have reſcu'd my Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Apology from the Vulture-Talons of the Reflector, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Self-and-all-contaminating Harpy, come off Victor, or die on the Stage.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:133463:2"/>
            <head>The CONFLICT.</head>
            <p>THE grand, and ſole Charge (whereof the Reflector eſſays to give Proof) againſt the Apology, is leeſing-making, <hi>i. e.</hi> telling of Lies, which in <hi>Scotland</hi> being made Treaſon, 'tis the Apologiſt's Mercy his Tryal is at an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bar. Two Inſtances hereof are quoted with hideous Out-cry: One in <hi>pag.</hi> 4. of the Apology, reſpects <hi>David Cairns,</hi> Eſquire; the other in <hi>pag.</hi> 23. the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin.</hi> To both in general, I ſay, there is not a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of either in the Original Copy of the Apology, which is yet extant, and whence the Printed Copy was taken. To the latter I ſhall Anſwer anon in due place: The former in <hi>pag.</hi> 4. Argument Fourth, runs thus [in ſpecial Counſellor <hi>Cairns,</hi> who declar'd for the then Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; who form'd the Multitude into Companies, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter locking the Gates.] The ſtyle as well as matter of theſe words, with the exact antitheſis in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and fore-going parts of that Paragraph (theſe words excluded) may convince any Judicious Reader, they were inſerted by a different hand. Not the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to whom the Apology was directed, not the Book-ſeller, nor the Printer, and leaſt of all Mr. <hi>Cairns,</hi> to whoſe Style and Senſe they bear no Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, who is much a Sufferer by them, though he knew nothing of 'em before he had it from the Preſs. But whoe're inſerted them, where lies the falſhood that has rais'd ſuch a Duſt, occaſion'd ſo much Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour? Where? firſt, 'tis ſaid, Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> declar'd (when he only by private Diſcourſe endeavour'd to influence both City and Country) for the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion. Again, 'tis ſaid, Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> form'd the Multitude into Companies after the Gates were lock'd. He ſhould have ſaid, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the Multitude of their Intereſt and Duty, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited them by Arguments and his own Concurrence, to purſue with Conſtancy the good Cauſe they had ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly eſpous'd. The truth of this paſſage, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects Mr. <hi>Cairns,</hi> is this: He was out of the City when the Gates were lock'd, but arriving the next hour, and being mighty well pleas'd at the Action, and Reſolution of the Actors, but finding none of the grave Citizens with thoſe brisk Juniors, walk'd with them round the Walls and Gates of the City, anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to perfiſt in their Vigour and Reſolution for the Proteſtant Religion, their Country, (and as far as he durſt whiſper it) for the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, Protector of both. Having left them in the Guard-Houſe, he made it his next buſineſs to engage the Chief Citizens in the ſame Cauſe, ſome of which accompany'd him to the Guard-Houſe the ſame Night, joyn'd with him in giving Encouragement and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to thoſe Juniors: He with others wrote that Night to ſeveral Gentlemen in the Country, ſolliciting their Concurrence, and effectual Aſſiſtance. He alſo Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd the Biſhop, but without effect. This Account I have from good hands, and do Appeal to any Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petent Judge, whether it do not juſtifie the attributing to Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> the equivalent at leaſt, tho' not the ſame, which the Inſertor, in ſomewhat a Ruſtic ſtyle, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements him with. But Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindicator tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends the Reflector and all others on this head, and ſays (<hi>pag.</hi> 26.) the Apologiſt aſcribes that to Mr. <hi>Cairns,</hi> as ſingle, which he always own'd, was done by joynt-conſent with others. Aſcribes? where? Either in the words now vindicated, or no where: Aſcribes? what? The Honour of that firſt Action. How is that poſſible, when nothing is attributed to him, till after locking the Gates, which ſure was the commencement of that firſt Action? Aſcribes to him as ſingle? Strange! when all is aſcrib'd to him in conjunction with a plurality. To give Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> the firſt room of either Citizens or Gentlemen of chief Note, that firſt influenc'd, countenanc'd, and concur'd with thoſe Juniors men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, is no more than his due; unleſs the meer lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gates engroſs all the Honour of that Action: But to infer hence, the Apology aſcribes that Honour to him as ſingle, when it firſt makes him but one, (tho' a Chief and Leading Man) of the firſt Actors; and next mentions him relatively to a multitude, and both in part of one Period, is a new mode of deducing Conſequences I never before this heard of. Nor can I divine what the Gentleman infers his [as ſingle] from, unleſs it be the Infertor's [in ſpecial Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi>] that is eſpecially, chiefly, or principally Mr. <hi>Cairns,</hi> I cannot elſe underſtand it: But then, how all, or any of theſe Synonimous terms can mean Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> as ſingle, excluſive of all others, has puzl'd my Grammar and Logic, and ſome Learned Men I have conſulted about it; do therefore ſubmit this inference, with the Explication I have now given of that Paragraph, to the unprejudic'd Reader; to whom I ſhall give no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble in peruſing what I had prepar'd in Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of my firſt Plea for C. <hi>Walker,</hi> being reliev'd in part by Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication, and now ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded by the true Narrative laſt week Printed. Shall therefore pitch next in <hi>pag. 9th.</hi> of the Reflections, and make bold to reckon with the Reflector for his Leeſing-making. For, having quoted theſe words of the Apology [It will be found the Intereſt of Church and State, to Repeal the Act of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> as it reſpects that Order, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Biſhops,] he thus ſubjoyns, That is to ſay, to aboliſh Epiſcopacy, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them from the Houſe of Lords. I knew a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſe Man, who would ever begin his Elucidations and Expoſitions with a <hi>That is to ſay;</hi> who, tho' he never had a word to the purpoſe, yet often ſpake truth, was therefore by one half leſs unhappy than the Reflector, who rarely ſtumbles on either. What? Epiſcopacy and <hi>Scandalum Magnatum</hi> reciprocal terms? Muſt they ſtand and fall together? If they do, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:133463:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> my Vote for aboliſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>opacy, becauſe I would not aboliſh Presbytery, which is or ſhould be the ſame. Biſhop and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are made the ſame by two Apoſtolical Acts, both Prior to the Act of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum.</hi> The firſt, <hi>Act Apoſtol. Cap. viceſ. commate</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with <hi>Verſe</hi> 28. where our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlators, being by the Canons (I ſuppoſe) oblig'd to maintain a diſtinction of Order as well as Degree <hi>(jure divino)</hi> between Biſhop and Presbyter, tranſlated the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> Biſhops, by the word Overſeers; which with ſubmiſſion to their ſince-improv'd textual Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was ill done; for the moſt negligent Curate with greateſt over-ſight inſpects his Flock, and in a ſenſe is the greateſt Overſeer. The ſecond Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Act is that cited by the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Epiſtle to <hi>Titus, commate</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. compar'd with <hi>Verſe</hi> 7th. I might add ſeveral more from both St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but theſe two are ſufficient to prove Biſhop and Presbyter identifi'd by Apoſtolical Sanction, which to me is a <hi>Jus Divinum.</hi> But pray Reflector take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, when I ſay theſe Apoſtolical Acts are Prior to our Acts of Parliament, I mean, <hi>tempore,</hi> not <hi>digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> or <hi>authoritate;</hi> For I am not ignorant that our Religion in <hi>England</hi> (which holds alſo in Church-Government) is call'd the Eſtabliſh'd Religion, on the account of the Authority deriv'd to it from Acts of Parliament, but am withal aſſur'd, that the preſent Parliament (whatever may be ſaid of any former) pays a great deference to Apoſtolical Acts, eſpecially when cited with ſuch convincing Evidence as I have theſe two.</p>
            <p>My Second Plea for Col. <hi>Walker</hi> conſiſted in this, <hi>i. e.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Eccleſiaſtic Superiours, and chiefly that very Reverend Prelate from <hi>Ireland,</hi> who receiv'd Col. <hi>Walker</hi> into his Coach at <hi>Barnet,</hi> and under whoſe Conduct he was obſerv'd to Compile his Narrative, are the Principal Authors of the Miſrepreſentations charg'd on his Narrative. And do's the Reflector eſſay to diſprove it? No: he dares not deny it, nor ſo much as name the Plea; but diverts the Reader from taking any Notice of it, by a pleaſant Story. The Apologiſt's Informer miſtook it ſeems Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi>'s Coach for the Arch-Biſhop's; but the Reflector aſſures you, the Coach was Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi>'s, for (ſays he) I ſaw it. And then (as if the Plea de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd all validity and ſtrength from this Circumſtance) he ſubjoyns very Comically [So that if Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> be an Arch-Biſhop, he carries a Cloak over his Pall, and ſtands in need of a Diſpenſation for his Lay-Habit. I have heard of a Padder, that us'd to wear a Biſhop's Gown and Sleeves over a Buff Coat, as often as he examin'd the Travellers Pockets: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Long-run catch'd, the Gentleman was hang'd; whether the Sacred Veſtures were hang'd with him, or were conſecrated anew, and apply'd to their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Uſe, I cannot ſay, for I ſaw it not, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector ſays he did this Action: But I never till now, heard of a Knight in a Pall, nor an Arch-Biſhop in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ector's Fancy elevated him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bit above <hi>Mercury;</hi> but what retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Arch-Biſhop has made him for having lodg'd with his Grace (as Principal Author) the Failures of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, as did the Apologiſt, I know not; I on my part hereby render him my hearty thanks for having ſav'd me the labour of confirming my ſecond Plea. Nor is the Reflector leſs kind in confirming my firſt Plea for Col. <hi>Walker,</hi> tho' in ſomewhat a prepoſterous Method, and where he little intended it.</p>
            <p>That firſt Plea conſiſted of ſeven Arguments, evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that Col. <hi>Walker</hi> neither is, nor can be Author of that Narrative. And here the Reflector neither af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> wrote it, nor denies the contrary; nor ſo much as bids at one Argument, to prove him at all the Author of it; how then does he attempt an eſcape from the Apologiſt? as in the preceding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph he vainly hop'd to miſlead his Reader by a witty Story; ſo here he eſſays to divert him by this profound Query. Good Sir (ſays the Reflector) do me the favour to tell me, do you think Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> was the Compiler of that Narrative which paſſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Name, or no? Good Sir, do me the favour to tell me, whether it was Full Moon or Midnight, when you read my firſt Plea for Col. <hi>Walker,</hi> and firſt eight Pages of the Apology, both beſtow'd in evincing, he is not the Compiler of that Narrative? The Reflector proceeds in a very Logical, disjunctive diſtribution of his Query; If you do (ſays he) as in the former part of your Paper you ſeem to inſinuate) why do you Calumniate him for the Errors and Imperfections in it? I ſhall anon ſalute one or two of the Reflector's [it ſeems,] as to the term Calumniate, in my Opinion (as the Reflector has it of the word Abdicate) that Verb implies a ſpontaneous act and ſomewhat more; no leſs than a cooperation of the two Supream Powers of the Rational Soul, the Underſtanding, and Will, (a Calumny being confeſſedly an heinous immorality) but an Aſs, I mean of four Legs, can exert a ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Act, I am ſure the Reflector's Horſe could, if that Member of our Club was not miſtaken, in faying, he run away with the Reflector's Rational Faculty, which I thought had been impoſſible, but for a wing'd Poſt from the higher or lower Regions. Were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Suppoſition as true as 'tis falſe, it could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no more than a Miſtake or intellectual Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, not a Calumny; ſince it neither had, nor ever ſhall have the conſentient act of the Apologiſt's Will. But you, O Reflector, have calumniated the Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, Logical, Moral ſenſe of the Apology, the Senſe and Reaſon of all, and your own among others that read it, in ſuggeſting that it charges thoſe Errors and Imperfections in that Narrative on Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> when its main ſcope is to prove the contrary. And whereas you inſinuate, that I ſeem to ſuſpect Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Senſe or Courage; I tell you, of his Courage he has given ſufficient demonſtration in <hi>page</hi> 24 of his Narrative, where he ſays, he mounted one of the Horſes that were beaten to the Gates of <hi>Derry,</hi> and reliev'd Col. <hi>Murry,</hi> whom he ſaw ſurrounded with the
<pb facs="tcp:133463:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Name, with the colour of the Horſe which Mr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> mounted at the Gate, neither of which could I ever learn, tho' all the ſurviving Actors were Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated on that Head; nor does Col. <hi>Murry</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he ever but from that Narrative, heard that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> was that day on Horſe-back, or at all ſeen in any Sally, much leſs ſee him come to his Relief. The other, and (I fear deſign'd) is the Narrator's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concealing the greateſt act of Gallantry performed at <hi>Derry,</hi> or perhaps in <hi>Europe,</hi> theſe ſeven years paſt at leaſt, by one Man, <hi>i. e.</hi> Col. <hi>Murry</hi> his killing in that Sally General <hi>Mamow</hi> in a Perſonal Conflict, when the Colonel was deſerted by ſo many of his own Party (as that Narrative reports) and ſurrounded by the Main Body of the Enemy's Horſe. But to return to Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> I ſhould be very ſorry he ſhould not prove a Man of Senſe too; for I hope to live to ſee him ſit in the Houſe of Peers in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> or <hi>Dublin;</hi> and then every body would be apt to ſay, that the King had ſpoil'd a good Colonel, and an excellent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of a Gariſon, (I hate to ſay, a Careful and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Store-keeper, and diſtributer of Proviſions, as Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindicator, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. and 23.) to make an ill Biſhop, who would never be able to ſecure the Church from being crucified between Popery and Presbytery, as — between two Thieves, if he did not better plead her Cauſe than his Vindicator (that has ſcarce the Soul of an Inſect) does his Narrative. Mean while, Reflector, give me leave to tell you, that if I had been ſo credulous as to have believ'd Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> compil'd that Narrative, theſe two Paragraphs of yours I have now ſcann'd, would have reliev'd my miſtake, and confirm'd both Pleas of the Apology. I marvel your fertile Invention could not ſuggeſt to you, that once at leaſt in thoſe Weeks wherein Mr. <hi>C. &amp;c.</hi> were licking the Paper into the form of a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> might be ſeen with a Pen in his hand, and Paper before him to write a Letter at leaſt to ſome of his abſent Friends, and then a Man of the Reflector's Courage would never have fail'd ſolemnly to aver he ſaw him writing the Narrative. But where the Fancy is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitarian,</hi> and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">No where.</note>, ſuch ſlips are unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſo I paſs this of the Reflector. And now <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> I offer him another Argument to prove it impoſſible Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> ſhould compile that Narrative: The impoſſibility I infer from Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Circumſtances during his Government in <hi>Derry,</hi> and in <hi>London</hi> till the Narrative was publiſhed. 'Tis to be obſerv'd, that Col. <hi>Walker</hi> in his Government much Copied <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi>'s Platform of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, yet he preferr'd that of <hi>Numa Pompilius.</hi> I do not mean (far be it from me) that the Colonel had any Nocturnal Conſults with an <hi>Egerian</hi> Nymph; but my ſenſe is, that as the beſt Governours of Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons awake a Nights, and ſleep by Day; ſo the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel being much up, and at his buſineſs a-nights, muſt be much down a-days, by the Old Maxim, <hi>Quod caret alternâ requie durabile non eſt.</hi> Now, all the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Hiſtory of Actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, while he was aſleep. The Analogy betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi>'s Government and the Colonel's may likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in this, that as <hi>Numa</hi> introduc'd many new Religious Ceremonies in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo the Colonel one in <hi>Derry, i. e.</hi> whenever any Governour of <hi>Derry</hi> ſhall prefer a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the Office of Keeper of the Stores, ſuch Parſon, in Veneration to his Gown, ſhall paſs for Principal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and enjoy the Honour of Priority in all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Orders and Subſcriptions. But this I paſs, for I can't bear, Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> ſhould be neither Keeper of Men nor Sheep, but of ſome Belly-Timber, and a little Powder and Ball; and my Argument will ſtand impregnable without it, from the Colonel's Circumſtances in <hi>London,</hi> during the patching up of that Narrative; for as it had been a mercileſs Cruelty to have impos'd that Task upon him immediately after the Fatigue both of the Siege and his long Journey, ſo if he had attempted it, he had undoubtedly prov'd <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> before its accompliſhment. For his day-hours (till after it was Printed) were beſtow'd partly at Court, about State-Affairs, but principally in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing Public Entertainments with a more Public, yet never-ſatiating view of his own never-enough ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd Perſon, who had much ſurpaſs'd in Warlike Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ay, and <hi>Hercules</hi> too with his Twelve Labours, though the Son of the beſt and biggeſt <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Pray read <hi>pag.</hi> 2. of his before-cited Obſervations. <hi>Mr.</hi> Walker <hi>was the man — whoſe Prodigious Actions no Age nor Hiſtory can paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, and which create credibility even in the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable Romances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have in the Apology, and in this Vindication (both confirm'd by the Reflector) plac'd it beyond all Suſpicion (though one Caſe-hardned <hi>Nego</hi> would have ſerv'd the turn) that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> wrote not that Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. And yet, leſt it ſhould be turn'd into an Old Almanac before it has ſerv'd its Year, and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the Copy break the Printer, I'le put the Reflector into a method, that may a little retrieve its Reputation with ignorant (<hi>i. e.</hi> the greater number of) Readers for ſome time. Let him Purchaſe two Witneſſes with the following Qualifications: Firſt, they muſt be no Gown-men, therefore no Women, Clergy-men, nor Lawyers; they may were Coats, but not of the Souldiers Faſhion, leſt they be ſuſpected of having ſerv'd the Colonel in <hi>Derry,</hi> and to have been ſuborn'd: They may wear Cloaks, but not of the ſame Faſhion with Knights, leſt they have a Pall under them; the Presbyterian Cut will do beſt of any: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus array'd, they muſt appear in the Lower Houſe of Convocation, (<hi>i. e.</hi> when they ſhall ſit next) and ſtanding before the Prolocutor's Chair, after they have turn'd up their Whiskers, and gravely ſtrok'd their Beards, <hi>(Tacto quinetiam collari Penulae Presbyterianae, minimè vero paginâ Sacrâ, nè, ſi fortè manus, in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum Tobit, aperto nimirum codice, delaberetur, jurarent per creaturam, quod, ne fiat, jure Canonico veteri, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi cautum eſt poena)</hi> they muſt hold forth, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb facs="tcp:133463:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Glaſs in his left, and Pen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mouth, write that Narrative, five Pound of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Thouſand will precure him two Witneſſes thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>alified in <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed with the Reflector, who <hi>page</hi> 10. taxes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny ſincerity, in a very weighty point. The Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſuppoſes the Biſhops advice to the Citizens was deliver'd immediately before locking the Gates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he aſſures us 'twas ſome hours after. This is a very momentous circumſtantial miſtake, I therefor thank him for Correcting it. But by his miſappli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Term Sincerity, and that of Calumny a little before, the Reflector ſeems to be as much a Stranger to the Notion of the Moral and Theological Vertues, as he is practically converſant in their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Vices. I wonder he ſhould ſo much miſtake the Notion of Sincerity, the moſt comprehenſive, or rather the form of all Graces and Vertues: when, as I ſhall all along to the end of this Pamphlet ſhew, there is neither Vertue, nor Vice ſo familiar to him as the oppoſite Vice of Sincerity: whereof in his ſubſequent Words he gives us an Inſtance; where he charge me with the partial aſcription of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of looking the Gates of <hi>Derry</hi> (intirely) to Mr. <hi>Irwin:</hi> Whereas the Apology expreſly ſaies <hi>page</hi> 14. Mr. <hi>Irwin with ſome others of his Fellows locked all the Gates.</hi> The Reflector <hi>page</hi> 15. owns the truth of the paſſage related of the Biſhop of <hi>Derry. It is true</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Biſhop left the City, being not able to influence the Citizens with his Doctrin: But what then? Why ſo many words, and ſo much notice taken of this ſingl? Action?</hi> Well pleaded, Reflector on behalf of the Biſhop: What then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector? Becauſe I would hope your Queſtion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds more from pitiable Weakneſs then from unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Malice to the King an Kingdoms, I will tell you, had the Biſhops Doctrin taken place, and <hi>Derry</hi> been ſurrendred to <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> what Power, or Policy, Humanely Speaking, could have prevented King <hi>James</hi> his being in undiſturb'd Poſſeſſion of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the firſt of <hi>May</hi> laſt? Not <hi>Inneskilling,</hi> I trow; not our Army that Arrived in <hi>Ireland</hi> in nine Months after locking <hi>Derry</hi> Gates. And if that King had then been poſſeſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> how eaſily might he by Tranſporting but a third of his Army laſt Summer, recover <hi>Scotland</hi> too? What could have retarded his Progreſs in that Kingdom, but that great body of Presbyterians in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as their Brethren did in the North of <hi>Ireland?</hi> What the conſequence would have been in <hi>England</hi> before this, conſidering what Intereſt King <hi>James</hi> had then, <hi>(horreſco referens)</hi> ſtill has in this Iſle, all good Men dread and deteſt: So much in anſwer to your wiſe Query. My temptation to mention the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Speech, was the affinity of ſome of the Crimes falſly charged by the Narrative on Mr. <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</hi> with the Biſhops Doctrin and after depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Derry.</hi> Of Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi> I need not, ſhall not now ſay any thing; but as to the very Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that I am beyond all ſcruple perſwade, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever his Speech, and ſubſequent demeanour (ſuppoſing a compliance in the Citizens) had proved pernicious to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and dangerous to the three Kingdoms, yet what he ſaid and did in that juncture, was the conſequent of the Dictat of a real not pretended Conſcience, which is the proximat rule of all both Religious and Moral Actions: that as Univerſal ſuffrage gives him the character of a very Learned, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily-Pious, Induſtrious, Preaching Prelate; ſo I firmly believe him as Loyally affected to the preſent Government, of a Temper as moderate, Pacifick, as fit an Inſtrument to reconcile and unite divided Proteſtants as any of his Gown. This much I ſent to the Preſs after the Apology, but it came too late. The Reflector proceeds. But what? Could he find never a Text in Scripture pat to his purpoſe, but muſt ſully the cleanneſs of his Apology by a prophane Heathen Poet? Yes, I could find one in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour.</hi> And another ſomewhere in the eighth of Saint <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt. But I made a ſcruple of ſullying (indeed prophaning) Scripture with the ſubject of the Apology, in which nothing occurred properly Sacred, except a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Arch-Biſhop and Gown: and I could not find ſo much as one name of any of the three in Sacred Code. For, the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only Scripture in the New Teſtament alledg'd for the Ceremonies, was by Mr. <hi>H. Jeans</hi> a Presbyterian Miniſter, twiſted out of the great <hi>Hamonds</hi> hands, and I am afraid it will never be retriev'd unleſs Dr. <hi>Beveridg</hi> make it the Text for his next <hi>Concio ad Clerum;</hi> but had your pretty Story of the Cloak and Pall been Printed before the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, I could have prevailed with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to vouch for the Cloak, and I could have turn'd the Pall into Parchment, and then it would bear a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſtamp, tho' the Arch-Biſhop (I mean the Knight) remained <hi>prophane,</hi> (I mean) <hi>lay ſtill.</hi> The Reflector ſubjoyns, it is a far fetcht alluſion (he means my lines out of <hi>Juvenal</hi>) and as juſtly and patly I may retort from Verſes of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Scilicet horreres, majoraque monſtra putares,</l>
               <l>Si mulier Vitulum, vel ſi bos ederet agnum.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juven. Sat. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Monſtrous patly Reflector, and very modeſtly ſaid of your ſelf: but whether the following Diſtic had not been more pat, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Obſervator eram, ſum, non vir, non Cacodaemon,</l>
               <l>Non bos, non Mulier, ſed pro re quilibet horum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:133463:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> till you make go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one in your firſt Paragraph; till then not a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>London</hi> or <hi>London-Derry</hi> will purchaſe them at a Cann of Ale per do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen. Proceed we next to my Ten Queries which the Reader will do well to take a view of in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, and next of the Reflectors wiſe Remarques on them.</p>
            <div n="1" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERE. <hi>I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I give the Reflector my devout thanks for confirming the grand import of the Firſt Query. I likewiſe grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accept his pains in correcting in words at length the carleſs Printers additional Cypher, though the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt Reader muſt obſerve the miſtake. But he having yielded, the number of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter, Scots,</hi> laſt year to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to an Hundred Thouſand; in the ſame Paragraph to ſuggeſt the Service of thoſe in <hi>Derry</hi> and <hi>Inniskilling</hi> was performed by Gentlemen of another Nation and Perſwaſion, beſpeaks him a Man of a very hard Fore-head, but ſomewhat a Phlegmatic brain; for, as the ſuggeſtion in the latter part of the Paragraph ſubverts the conceſſion in the former: ſo the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all concerned in thoſe two places for proof of it, is an inſtance of confidence paralell'd only in thoſe two already quoted out of his Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But 'tis very probable he writ his Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with a Steel Pen, which gives him ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of me, that uſe only a Gooſe-quil. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation of a deſign in the Apologiſt to create dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and jealouſies between the two Nations, the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is a Calumny I deteſt and ſhall anon fully purge my ſelf off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY. <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Reflector, inſtead of giving a direct Anſwer to the ſecond Query (his invention failing him) fondly hopes to miſlead the Reader by a very pleaſant (I ſay not ridiculous) Queſtion, <hi>i. e. Whether the Presbyterian Perſwaſion be the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Property of a</hi> Scotch-Man? <hi>Whether Presbyter and Scot be terms convertible?</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Categorically; no, for the fourteen Biſhops Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated in <hi>Thirty-Eight</hi> by the National Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly in <hi>Glaſco,</hi> were all Scotch-men as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and the fourteen caſhir'd by Parliament laſt year, I think are all Scotch-men, yet no Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. I further anſwer, King <hi>James</hi> the Sixth who was a Learned Prince, and well underſtood the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical property of a Scotch-man, took (it ſeems) Presbyter and an honeſt Scot (underſtood of the Clergy) for terms convertible: for when ſome bold Scot preſumed to ask His Majeſty, why he would make ill men Biſhops? He anſwered (as I have often heard from grave Men of that Nation) by his Saul he was forced to make Knaves Biſhops, for he could not get one honeſt man in <hi>Scotland</hi> that would take a Biſhoprick. Now I confeſs I pay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> honeſt Biſhops, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Son and Grandſons, he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> demonſtration they would give him, that Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian is not the Logical property of an honeſt Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And yet, will I venture the Apology againſt your Reflections, that is ten to one with the Bookſeller, that the Caſe being fairly ſtated, as in the Apology you find (and dare not ſo much as ſcratch at) it, the twentieth Soul of any Rank or Nation in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that have any real raſt of Serious Religion falls not to the Churches ſhare: There is therefor not one word of pertinent truth in your Anſwer, being intirely beſides my Queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY. <hi>III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The third Query is a dark riddle to the Reflector: I profeſs I cannot help it, for I neither have, nor know where to beg, buy, or borrow a light or clear Riddle: Nor dare I be ſo unmerciful to my ſelf, as to be at the pains to unriddle this Query, having had task enough to prepare nine Queſtions all ſpig-and-ſpan-new for the Reflector and his Learned Club, to reſolve, without being at the drudgery to anſwer 'em my ſelf. But in charity to the Reflector do adviſe him hereafter not to quote unneceſſarily (I ſay not Impertinently) that diſtinction, between the Perſonal and Politic Capacity of a King, till his improv'd Judgment and Learning qualify him to refute it; and then, I'm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident he will let it reſt till he has gone firſt to his own reſt or laſt receptacle. Nor will I accept his witty (forſooth) Application of it as a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent evidence that he ever underſtood conſcentious fighting, much leſs actually did conſcientiouſly fight for King <hi>Charles,</hi> or his Sovereign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY <hi>IV.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whether the ſame or a different Genius inſpired the Reflector when he wrote his Remarks on the fourth Queſtion, and his firſt Paragraph, I cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine: if a different, then without queſtion his evil Genius ſuggeſted the former, and his good the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but if one inſpired both, to be ſure it was one of the <hi>Elfs</hi> of that pragmatical Legion he drove to the Northern Regions, which brought ſeven Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits more robuſt than it ſelf, to avenge the affront on the Reflector. <hi>Omne malum a Septentrione.</hi> In his firſt Paragraph he makes the Apologiſt guilty of what not towards his Sovereign; here he ſays of him [<hi>he</hi> i. e. <hi>the Apologiſt ſo generally abſolves our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign</hi>] but I do aſſure the Reflector I ſhall not abſolve him, nay I impeach him of, and retort upon him the ſame Crimes, <hi>i. e. his moſt rudely, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationally, but very bluntly treating his Sovereign.</hi> The Impeachment conſiſts of two Articles. Firſt, He makes his Sovereign a Tranſgreſſor, for, where there is no Tranſgreſſion, there can be no Abſolution: Where, by the way I would know of the Reflector,
<pb facs="tcp:133463:5"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>England:</hi> If the former, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ridiculous has he made himſelf, by ridiculing the diſtinction between the Kings Perſonal and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic Capacity, or <hi>Charles</hi> and Sovereign. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Article is his <hi>Innuendo</hi> of the Kings receiving Abſolution, <hi>i. e.</hi> Pardon from a Subject. Both Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are prov'd by his own words now quoted. I might add a third, That he affirms Abſolution given, without inquiring whether the Abſolver be a Prieſt or no. I might further impeach the Reflector of palpable prevarication; for in the ſame Sentence wherein he makes me an Abſolver of my Sovereign, the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Diſſenters, I expreſly Abſolve the Moderat Conformiſts, which he ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conceals. Therefor the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he civilly ſays, <hi>I maliciouſly intend to caſt the guilt and odium upon,</hi> can be no other than the Immoderate Conformiſts; to whoſe bounty I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the Reflector for a reward of his good Service. Nor will I impeach his <hi>Ergo,</hi> as illogical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferred, becauſe he ſeems to have borrowed his Mode of Syllogizing from the before mentioned King <hi>James</hi> his Dogs, who at a fault, thus argued with their noſes, the Hare did not run this way, nor that way, tarbox the third way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5,6" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY <hi>V. VI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Reflector being agreed with me in the Fifth Query, I muſt attend his reſolution of the Sixth. I appeal to the Reader, whether in his Reflections on this and the following Queries, he has not given me the fareſt advantage, as well as higheſt provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to treat him as an open enemy of common Civility, and Morals. Yet in the whole has he proved ſo kind to me, ſo unkind to himſelf, tho he intended neither, that I very gratefully reſent both. Obſerve how here (as under the former Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) he conceals, my more generous abſolving Act (ſince ſuch he'l have it) of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both Clergy and Laity; having alſo concealed my Queſtion, he gives three of his own, inſtead of an Anſwer to that one of mine. To all which I anſwer in a word, that Diſſenters cannot be ſaid to be in an equal capacity with other Proteſtant Subjects to embarque in any Publick Service, while the Sacrament Teſt continues in force. I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire the Reflector, <hi>not for ſhame, I come too late for that, but for ſecurity to his remaining credit, to retract this injurious Calumny of his.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY. <hi>VII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>My Seventh Query runs thus, whether, <hi>if all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects were equally forward with the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for the Service of the King, Kingdoms, and Proteſtant Religion, the many effects there mention'd</hi> (of ineſtimable conſequence to their Majeſties and Kingdoms) <hi>would not follow?</hi> but the Reflector <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to the Diſſenters a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis are <hi>(excluding other Proteſtant Subjects)</hi> What? exclude other Proteſtant Subjects, when the expreſs ſcope of the Queſtion is to include them? What elſe were this, but to exclude my own ſenſe, and intendment from the Query, and to include non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe and contradiction? Now would I know, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Reflector when he thus miſrepreſented my Queſtion in a ſenſe repugnant to the very Grammer of my words, did underſtand their litteral ſenſe or not? if the latter, I both pardon him and heartily pray for an advance of his intellectuals: But if the former, then I freely allow him an overmatch for the moſt Ingenious and Learned of Mankind, that confine themſelves to Truth for the Matter, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Rule of what they write; and therefore I yield him the Buckler. And to his forreign and far fetched double Queſtion; Firſt, <hi>Whether I do not take Major - General</hi> Ludlow <hi>to be a Diſſenter?</hi> I Anwſer, I take him for neither Diſſenter nor Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, becauſe dead in Law, and at preſent not in or of the Kingdoms. Cannot divine why he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions him on this ſubject, unleſs it be an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of meeting with ſomewhat in my Anſwer, that may purchaſe him the honourable Office of an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But I ſhall fruſtrate his hopes. His Second Query is, <hi>Whether I did not tacitly glance at M. G. L. to have the chief Conduct of the Army or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy?</hi> A tacit glance? I had thought <hi>taciturnity</hi> reſpected the Organ of <hi>Speech, glancing</hi> that of <hi>Sight.</hi> But now I think on't, the ingenious <hi>Cowley</hi> ſomewhere tells us of words that weep, and tears that ſpeak, and ſo I paſs it. To the Queſtion I anſwer Categorically, I neither have ſeen, or had any Correſpondence by Letters or otherwiſe with M. G. <hi>L.</hi> while he was laſt in <hi>England,</hi> nor had him once in my thoughts that I can remember, while I was ſcribling the Apology. But the Reflector ſays, <hi>that what he inſinuates in his double Query, is reported to be the declar'd Opinion of the Apologiſt.</hi> Reported by whom? by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector, or a Knight of the Poſt? If he finds a third Perſon, and of a different Genius, I'le be content to ſuffer for M. G. <hi>L.</hi> But that I may Oblige the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector with ſomething his Invention may enlarge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Metamorphoſe into various ſhapes, I'le adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to tell him, that if M G. L. had gone for <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Quality of Major-General of our Army (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Auſpice of King <hi>William</hi>) laſt Year, and landed any time before the laſt of <hi>May</hi> with a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe, ten Thouſand Foot, with Arms for Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thouſand more, nothing but the unfitneſs of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants there for a Deliverance could have prevented his Reducing and Subjecting that Kingdom entirely to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown, and driving all the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> into the Boggs or Sea. The Reaſon ſupporting my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, That the Rebels of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the laſt Rebellion were ſubdu'd, and that Kingdom reduc'd only by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of <hi>England, i.e.</hi> the Army of the Rump-Parliament, as the Reflector calls it; and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels ſtand not in ſuch dread of treble the number of any that ſerv'd
<pb facs="tcp:133463:5"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſo heartily engage in that Service with Major-General <hi>Kirk</hi> as with Major-General <hi>Ludlow.</hi> But remember, Reflector, I ſpeak of what M. G. <hi>L.</hi> might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief laſt year, not this: For, after the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment's Addreſſing to the King (as you have it) for his Apprehenſion, I can promiſe nothing for him but that he ſhall be hang'd, if we can catch him handſomly on <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ground. Nor ſhall he have any thing from me but my Prayers (which even my Enemies ſhare in) that he may Repent; you know the Apoſtle tells us, it is the Divine Will, <hi>that all men come to Repentance.</hi> — And that he may obtain Mercy, as our Liturgy teaches me to pray — <hi>That it would pleaſe thee to have mercy on all men;</hi> and he muſt be a Man, and a ſtout ſturdy Fellow too, that prov'd ſuch a K— killing Rebel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY <hi>VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Reader may obſerve how the Reflector im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd the ſame Art here he us'd in his Reflections on the former Query; for he tells you, Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>pag.</hi> 16. — it ſeems to be intended by the connexion of the Apologiſt's Diſcourſe, that thoſe five Thouſand, or ten Thouſand Men, (at the Head of whom General <hi>Schomberg</hi> might have perform'd ſuch wonderful Exploits) ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt wholly of Diſſenters. It ſeems, good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector, to whom? Not to Angel or Man I'm well aſſur'd; not to Angels, no, not to the laps'd Tribe; for even theſe retain their Rational Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, can read and underſtand <hi>Engliſh:</hi> not to any man in his Wits, for the quite contrary ſenſe is as plain as words can make it; not to any man out of his Wits, for if ſuch cannot apprehend the plaineſt ſenſe, much leſs an obſcure, yea, impoſſible, which no Grammar nor Logic can give any colour to, which the Reflector gives my words; I conclude therefore, the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's it ſeems, ſeems ſo to neither Angel nor Man, wiſe or otherwiſe; <hi>Ergo,</hi> not to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector himſelf. I remember, <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> in his Sums, begins his Reſolutions of all Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with a <hi>Videtur,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it ſeems: But if the Reflector tacitly glanc'd at him, he is none of the happieſt in imitation; for <hi>Aquinas</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes his [it ſeems] to an Heterox Opinion, he finds, or ſuppoſes in his Antagoniſt, and having refuted it, he ſubſtitutes the Opinion he takes for Orthodox, and confirms it: But the Reflector conceals the true, ſubſtitutes an Heterox, and then expoſes it; that is, it ſeems, would murther my Legitimate Off-ſpring, place in their room the ſpurious Births of his own Brain, and oblige me to maintain the ſuppoſititious Brats. It ſeems <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in defiance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Angelical Intelligence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY <hi>IX.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I paſs the Reflector's it ſeems, on the Ninth Query; and paſs to his [I dare boldly ſay] only could wiſh he had ſubjoyn'd [any thing] which every body would believe; whereas now I can perſwade no body, no, not himſelf, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any thing he ſays, atteſts, conteſts, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts againſt the Apology. I have before ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, the Reflector can act the Woman's part, as well as the Man's; and here he gives you a pat Inſtance; for laying aſide his bold Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Averments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Rhetoric of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Lady, he thus makes his moan: <hi>Little did I think over to ſee the Spirit of</hi> William Prynn <hi>reviv'd.</hi> — Little did I think that Spirits could be ſeen by the Reflector, who cannot ſee the plaineſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Characters in Print: I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thought, that Bodies veſted with ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, were the Objects of ſight: but now I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, the Ingenious Dr. <hi>H. Moor,</hi> ſomewhere aſcribes ſome kind of (I know not what) Body to Spirits, and with Reaſon ridicules the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens idle Debate about a Thouſand Angels dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Galliard on the point of a Needle, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a decorum, without breaking their ſhins, or joſtling one another out of their places. But leaving this to the Philoſophers, I cannot yield <hi>William Prynn</hi>'s Spirit reviv'd, till the Reflector has prov'd the Soul dies, which neither the Old Hereticks, nor <hi>Muggliton</hi> of late could ever prove. And though I ſhould grant all this, yea, that the Reflector had the Courage to look <hi>William Prynn</hi>'s grim, black, ſtern, terrible Ghoſt in the Face, which no body will grant me, what then? What tricks did the Specter play? The Reflector tells us, he has ſcurrilouſly revil'd by the Apologiſt's Pen, the Function and Perſon of the Biſhops. If the Reflector allude (as I think he muſt) to Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> on-Biſhop'd, which he challenges the two Arch-Biſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York</hi> to Anſwer, the Reflector has very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily reviv'd the memory of that Book: For tho' there be ſome Arguments in it inconclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, there are many more, which as none (that I know of) have attempted to Anſwer, ſo ſhall I believe any ever will ſolidly when I ſee it, not before. As to the Reflector's Charge of Scurril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Calumny, and his demand to ſpecifie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons and Actions, after he has read them in the Query, and made his wiſe Reflections on 'em, he ſpeaks indeed like himſelf, and ſhall anon have a due Anſwer. Mean while let him know, that the Inſinuation reſpecting the three
<pb facs="tcp:133463:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be prov'd by men of, good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and unſuſpected Veracity; tho' I muſt withal declare, nothing ſhort of a juſt Reſentment of the manifeſt and very injurious miſrepreſentation of the Diſſenters in the Printed Narrative, and the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>T.</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern therein, could have extorted that ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Account of theſe great Prelates from me at this time. Come we next to that paſſage that reſpects the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin;</hi> this with the former relating to Mr. <hi>Cairns</hi> (accounted for) are the only inſtances impeach'd of falſhood in the Apology: Tho' the back-ſide Advertiſer has the Front to ſay, 'tis full of Lies. I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid, that neither of theſe paſſages are in the Original Copy of the Apology, but this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Printed Paper, I ſhall Account for it as I have for the former. The Reflector ſays, that what is here ſuggeſted (he'l by and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling his Art call it Averment) concerning the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> is a poſitive falſhood. How proves he the falſhood? The Commiſſioners appointed for diſtributing the Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Interrogated, and the Books ſearch'd, it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears he has not received one penny. But Reflector, your Interrogations and Search are beſides the purpoſe: For, can I ſuppoſe you ignorant that what money either that Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or ſome other Biſhops receiv'd of that Fund, falls not under the Cognizance of the Commiſſioners, nor is inſerted in the Book you mention. And I'le for once direct you to a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and eafier Method to diſprove the Suggeſtion. 'Tis but your going to the Arch-Biſhop, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with (that is, when you find his Grace at leiſure) to give you under his Hand, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Grace, nor any other Perſon, in his Name, by his Order, with his Privity or Conſent, has receiv'd, nor ſignifi'd his expectation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any money out of that Fund, for his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence ſince his arrival. And when ſuch Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificat is procur'd (which will be a buſineſs of Deliberation, becauſe momentous) it will no more prove the Suggeſtion a poſitive falſhood in the Inſertor, than your Interrogations and Search a poſitive Fallacy in you. The words of the Apology are theſe; <hi>The Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Dublin — <hi>has receiv'd of our Publick Fund of Charity to diſtreſſed Proteſtants from</hi> Ireland, <hi>not above a Thouſand Pounds, that be,</hi> i.e. <hi>the Book-ſeller, can bear of.</hi> Now, Reflector, improve your Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar and Logic (if any man alive can transform a plain truth into a poſitive falſhood, you can) and try whether you can ſqueeze out of theſe words any other meaning than a Suggeſtion (which you ſtill your ſelf call an Averment) of the Inſertor's having heard, that the Arch-Biſhop receiv'd the mention'd Sum. That the Inſertor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tive a truth, as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yours a poſitive falſhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="query">
               <head>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERY <hi>X.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In his Reflections on the Tenth Query, he ſays, <hi>I own my ſelf of the Presbyterian Perſwaſion,</hi> tho' he neither in terms read, nor by Logical conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can infer from any thing in the Apology what Perſwaſion I'm of. However, I own he has done me a greater Honour than he has done the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in pretending himſelf as well her Champion, as one of her Sons. Nor am I offended at his ſuſpecting me to be a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>William Penn,</hi> for therein he ſeems to ſuppoſe me his own Condiſciple; there being that I know of, not a Man in <hi>England</hi> the Reflector ſo much imitates in ſtyle as <hi>W. P.</hi> Either of 'em has <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rhetoric enough for two Orators, but both too little Logic, Natural and Artificial, for one freſh man. He further ſuſpects the Apologiſt to be a Diſciple of <hi>Ignatius Loyola;</hi> which is monſtrous ſtrange: Sure he forgot the fag-end of his famous Paragraph, and the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Advertiſer his Friend. This frequent ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contradiction in the ſame Pamphlet, verifies the Old Saying, <hi>That ſome men had need of a good Memory.</hi> However I'le be kind to the Reflector and Advertiſer, and will ſecure 'em from all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion of Jeſuitiſm. The Chriſtian World knows to its coſt, that Blaſphemous Seat entertains very ſew Fops or <hi>Ignoramuſes;</hi> and tho' thoſe two Gentlemen, eſpecially the Reflector, may vie for Courage againſt Senſe and Reaſon, and his own Conſcience too, with the hardieſt of 'em; yet I that know them, durſt not venture his Conduct againſt a Novice of that Sect. The Reflector proceeds, and ſuggeſts, <hi>That the Apology charges the Biſhops with beſtowing two or three Years pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation for one Conſecration-Sermon:</hi> This ſeems to be the ſenſe of his words, which I am not willing to impeach of Nonſence. Now, this pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable miſrepreſentation muſt proceed either from a weakneſs of Judgment, which neither Boy nor Girle of common ſenſe could be guilty of; or from a defect in Morals, which any wearing the Proteſtant Livery but the Reflector and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſer would bluſh at. Let the Reflector chooſe whether of the two beſt pleaſe him. I proceed to account (this being the proper place) for that paſſage in the Apology, which mentions the Odium incurr'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — And here I do ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly and ſincerely declare, that neither in this paſſage, nor any other in the Apology, I made the leaſt Reflection on the Eſtabliſht Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor any Member of her Communion, but thoſe alone, who deriving Authority from <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, or rather in his Reign from
<pb facs="tcp:133463:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>England,</hi> and Perſecuted at leaſt in Name, as well ſome of the beſt Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I need not here name, as the Diſſenters in Name, Perſon, and Eſtate; who have manifeſted diſaffection to the Preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, obſtruct the Union of the Proteſtants, the Tranquillity and Floriſhing of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Their Majeſties Proſperous Reign. Nor do's the Apology bear near ſo hard upon thoſe men, as many other Papers writ as well ſince as beofre it was publiſh'd, by very Learned, Reverend Sons of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I'le name but two of many, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>'s Sermon, and Dr. <hi>Carſwell</hi>'s. And why that ſhould be made a Crime in the Apologiſt, which is eſteem'd meritorious in other men, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not. Let theſe Gentlemen Reconcile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the preſent Government, and thereby to their Brethren, who are juſtly entitl'd to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination (taken <hi>à meliori parte</hi>) of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Church of <hi>England;</hi> and then may they aſſure themſelves of a juſt Veneration from all Proteſtant Churches, with the beſt Service of all true Proteſtants, and of the Apologiſt, who I hope may paſs for one, tho' of the loweſt Form. The Provocation to my inſerting that ungateful Paſſage in the Apology is too obvious to need another: But as to the Occaſion, beſides my own Obſervations, and the ſeveral Papers I had with regret read of our Murmurers, that Letter from a Miniſter of State abroad, to a Perſon of Honour in <hi>England,</hi> which you have in Number 14. of our New <hi>Scotch Obſervator,</hi> was freſh in my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; and tho' the Letter taxes the Nation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly with this murmuring Humour, Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without diſcriminating the Innocent Party or Principle from the Nocent; yet who knows not, the Impeachment can only reach that party of men now deſcrib'd, and intended in the Apology. By the way I would Adviſe the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Reader, to borrow (as I did) the aſſiſtance of a <hi>Scotch</hi> Interpreter to that Print, in which beſides the words <hi>[Communicate put for a Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, contrair, ungrate, reſiſtence]</hi> which are not <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the falſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> in miſ-ſpelling; the Phraſe gives a ſenſe ſometimes quite contrary to the Obſervator's Conceptions; as, when he would ſignifie, that Proteſtants abroad can ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, there ſhould poſſibly be found in <hi>England</hi> one (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſo much as one) ſingle Proteſtant diſſatisfi'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He has it <hi>[be found but one ſingle, &amp;c.]</hi> which in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Idiom implies a Plurality. Now, if he publiſhes Volumes (as he has one already) in this medly of <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> yet neither genuin <hi>Scotch</hi> nor <hi>Engliſh,</hi> what prejudice muſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue ſuſtain by it, which after theſe laſt Twenty Years re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> more eaſily tempt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pieces? 'Twere therefore to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>Hary</hi>'s Succeſtor, could at leaſt write true <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſince Nature has deny'd him the Wit, and his Education, perhaps his Years too, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral knowledge of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and Publick Affairs, theſe two Gentlemen were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of. But reſerving this Obſervator for another Occaſion, I return to the Reflector, who by <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end of his Prospective,</hi> could do wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fears in deſcribing the <hi>failures and miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of another Party.</hi> Let him begin when he will; that Party which I ſuppoſe he means bid him defiance, if he intend thoſe failures and miſcarriages with reſpect to the Government. As he goes on he repeats his own words in <hi>pag.</hi> 2. of his Obſervations before cited in celebrating Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s. extraordinary performances, <hi>which,</hi> ſays the Reflector — <hi>no Age nor Hiſtory can pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</hi> This Hyperbole might find ſome colour in Col. <hi>Murry,</hi> who was indeed the Man, whoſe Gallantry was not equal'd in <hi>Derry;</hi> by whoſe Loyalty and faithful Service, with thoſe that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her'd to him, <hi>Derry,</hi> and by conſequence the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was preſerv'd from being (once and again during the Siege) betray'd into the hands of King <hi>James;</hi> who better deſerv'd the Five Thouſand pounds, than Mr. <hi>W.</hi> did Five pounds. Conſult the true Narrative laſt Week Printed.</p>
               <p>The Apologiſt ſaid, that to believe what is attributed to the hand of the Church in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory Epiſtle prefix'd to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, requires equally with Tranſubſtantiation a Head abdicated of Reaſon and five Senſes. On which words the Reflector will play the Critic, <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>'tis not worth while. In my Opinion</hi> (ſays the Reflector) <hi>that word [abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat] cannot be apply'd in the paſſive ſenſe.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it implies a ſpontaneous Act.</hi> In my Opinion here is ſuch a piece of Criticiſm, as no Age nor Hiſtory can parallel. I nibbl'd at it an hour, but to no purpoſe, till I rais'd the Ghoſt of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Father, <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> the Prince of Critics, and Old <hi>Priſcian</hi>'s mangl'd Skull. And all three <hi>having piſs'd in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinal</hi> (as the Reflector has it) produc'd the Reflector's Critical Brat hopping upon theſe three Leggs, <hi>All-to be-p.</hi> No word (he means Verb) that implies a ſpontaneous act, can be apply'd in a paſſive ſenſe; but the Verb <hi>Abdicat</hi> implies a ſpontaneous act; <hi>Ergo</hi> cannot be apply'd in a paſſive ſenſe. Up ſtarts a <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy, and ſays, he would daſh out the Brains, and break all the Leggs and Limbs of the Reflector's Brat, ſo as <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> himſelf ſhould never bring it to Life again. Thus, ſays the Lad, the three
<pb facs="tcp:133463:7"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> taken in a paſſive ſenſe, now, for honeſt <hi>Litly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſake will I deny the Major, and challenge all the Logic in the Reflectors head to make it good.</p>
               <p>If he aver, that <hi>Amo</hi> implies a neceſſary, (not ſpontaneous) act in him, when an encharming Object preſents; <hi>Then</hi> (ſays the Lad) <hi>will I give him</hi> Verbero, which in our Venerable Dr. <hi>B.</hi> ſignifies a Spontaneous act, tho' to the Reflector a neceſſary act of Juſtice. But the Reflector for Illuſtration adds <hi>[A Man may be ſaid to abdicate, but not properly to be abdicated]</hi> the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy replies, the Reflector diſcovers his profound Ignorance of our common School Authors. Did he never read in <hi>Terence abdicare generum,</hi> and frequently in other Authors, <hi>abdicare filium, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum, &amp;c.</hi> in which Phraſes a Man is properly ſaid to abdicate and to be abdicated. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt anſwers, the Reflector makes himſelf the Man that abdicates and is abdicated; not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poligiſt, who makes reaſon the Abdicator, the head abdicated: And now adds the reaſon of his ſo doing; <hi>i. e.</hi> reaſon is properly the Man and King too of the <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> the Head his Throne, the whole Body his Kingdom. And therefore the Apologiſt wiſhes the Reflector to conſider whether his Head was not abdicated of Criticks and Latin, when he carp'd at that expreſſion and ſaid the word ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate is a new faſhion'd Word.<note place="margin">Vid. Quin' Juſtit. orat. <hi>p. 330.</hi> Senc. Phil. contro. cui titulus patruus abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans—&amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios paſſim.</note> The Reflector is nothing happier in taxing the word <hi>[ebibe]</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>between which and the word <hi>[imbibe]</hi> which wou'd have gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd the Reflectors Palate, there is as much difference as between ſipping and drinking a brimmer, and as his beloved Poet has it, <hi>Si trulla inverſo crepitum dedit aurea fundo;</hi> is therefor of the two the more emphatical to expreſs the Apologiſts ſenſe, and equally with the other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits enfranchiſment in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> City; eſpecially for the Reflectors Evening Service over a Bottle. The Reflectors Banter on the Apologiſts Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors us'd in aſſigning Thumb and Fingers to that Hand of the Church, diſcovers that <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtuff,</hi> and <hi>Canonical verity make but one</hi> Idea in the Reflectors underſtanding: but where he ſays the <hi>Apologiſt claps his wings, and crows like a Cock,</hi> I wiſh he had added <hi>a Comb,</hi> which the Reflector cou'd well have ſpar'd, and which alone wou'd have rendred me an equal match for the Reflector. I accept as a rarity the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectors Teſtimony, where he ſays <hi>The Apologiſts concluſion is very agreeable to the Premiſes;</hi> For the Premiſes being valid and immoveable the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> premiles, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I have flown in the face of the Government,</hi> he but ſays here what he proteſted in his firſt Famous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, and has in the body of his Pamphlet contradicted both. Whether in the whole he has one true period againſt the Apology, nay, has not confirm'd where he eſſay'd to confute it, <hi>I</hi> appeal to every unprejudic'd Reader. His Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is as deſperate as his Prologue is daring. He it ſeems loſt all hopes of making any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of all Impeachments, Averments, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefor as his laſt refuge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes him to the laſt weapon of an angry Female: <hi>i. e.</hi> a wiſh to the Apologiſt <hi>with Achitophel to hang himſelf,</hi> ſince the Reflector wants the courage, and can prevail with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to attempt the ſurly Fellow. Your wiſh Reflector is unſeaſonable, and I wiſh it may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prove ominous to your ſelf. In the laſt Reigns the beſt of Subjects were hang'd and otherwiſe cut off; but the compaſſionat Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us of our King ſpares notorious Rebels and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: There is therefore no danger I hope of the Apologiſt a true Man and a Loyal Subject, eſpecially, when ſo many falſe and difloyal at hand go unpuniſht. Now Reflector having won the Field, as I doubt not your ſelf with all men of Sence will own; I'l puniſh your inhumane Epilog with a very humane Chaſtiſement; that is give you your option of thoſe inflicted by <hi>Caligula</hi>'s Law on the foil'd Declamators at the famous Altar of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> To deſcribe thoſe ſeveral Puniſhments were to impeach your Hiſtorical acqueſts; but the eaſieſt and to you moſt eligible will be one of theſe two, either <hi>Orationem componere in laudem Victoris;</hi> or, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectiones in Apologiam ſpongiâ linguave delere.</hi> Remember Reflector, this gentle Correction is for paſt faults.</p>
               <p>For the future, I have a word to you at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; There is a Gentleman now in <hi>England,</hi> cloath'd with the Characters of <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Col. Govern. Counſel. you know him as you do any Man; pleaſe to give him my ſervice, and aſſure him 'tis <hi>as infallible a Truth as ever he aver'd,</hi> that out of reſpect to him, as Superviſor at leaſt, I have credited your Pamphlet with ſo civil an Anſwer; have omitted here to give you and it a counter Character with the return due to your extream demerits. But aſſure the Gentleman, if hereafter you or the back-ſide Advertiſer your Friend, vent againſt the Apology your peſtilential exhaltations, by either retail or wholeſale, ſheet or page, I ſhall do your three Pamphlets juſtice, and emblazon the Reflectors Virtues; in ſpecial, his tranſcendent Zeal and equal Courage againſt all degrees of Truth, the fixed dictates of his own practical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:133463:7"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Man, biggoted Papiſts only excepted. Shall ſhew withal, how far that Gentleman is intereſſed in the Reflectors Character, and the Remarks due to his performance; and ſo I bid you and him at preſent adieu.</p>
               <p>I am next to take notice of the credit Mr. <hi>Boyes</hi> has done the Apology, in borrowing from it the occaſion and not a little of the matter of his three pag'd Concluſion to his Vindication of Mr. <hi>Osh.</hi> which the Bookſeller has made a Six-Penny Book, as ſome others have the Apology; when each paper at half the price wou'd better have ſerved the Authors ends, and I doubt not the Bookſellers too. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> tell us a <hi>Relation of Mr.</hi> Wrs. <hi>has done him the honour</hi> (ironi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, as the ſequal explains it) <hi>to report him the Author of the Apology;</hi> but he ingenuouſly profeſſes <hi>he does not certainly know the Author,</hi> nor any thing of the Writing of it. I add, for his final Vindication, to this day he knows not who writ it. And here I wiſh he had ſtopt, and reſerv'd for ſome better occaſion thoſe feeble ſuccours, which want Nerves and Spirits requiſit to the pretended ſervice againſt the Advertiſement. their Center and Spring (I doubt) make but one point, tho' their Motion promiſe a different Period. Nor do's he beſtow a word in favour of the Apology, but what is depretiative of it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretiative of his own performance; as by a brief Survey of particulars will appear. He wou'd have it believ'd, <hi>The ſharp Advertiſement would help off the firſt Impreſſion of the Apology;</hi> whereas he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did or might know, the firſt Edition ſold ſo faſt that in four days there was Printed a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. He next deſcends to the two paſſages re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting Mr. <hi>Cairn's</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Dublin;</hi> which I have accounted for in this Paper, and have diſcover'd Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s Pen to be leſs fallible than the Apologiſts, who had no other Foundation to build upon, but ſome verbal Reports, with ſome few obſerves of his own; yet has not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of one Material error, much leſs a culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faſhood, in all that paper. Whereas Mr. <hi>B.</hi> has miſtaken the obvious Senſe of the former of theſe paſſages, as upon the place was ſhewn. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> might have ſpar'd calling any thing in that Advertiſement <hi>an ungrateful reproach;</hi> an Elogy from that Pen, I ſhould rather have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted ſuch to the Apologiſt. And however Mr. <hi>B.</hi> began early to diminiſh the Credit of the Apology, and would have Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> ſeem to deſpiſe, becauſe he could not Anſwer it; yet, he ſhou'd not have added of his own, that <hi>Mr.</hi> Wr. <hi>Conſign'd it into the hands of the Executioner;</hi> that being as much above his power, as its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit. In his placing the Apology among the <hi>little ſquabbles</hi> (by and by ill natur'd Subjects) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he beſtows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Anſwer (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Wrs.</hi> N. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Apology on the whole; and in vindicating one Non-conformiſt, than the Apology in vindicating (as far as was then proper) the whole party, including alſo his one. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> will be eas'd of his trouble about the Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when he has read his miſtake (of the Party he ſuppoſes reflected on) corrected in this Pamphlet. When he ſays, <hi>I perfectly Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi'd Mr.</hi> Wrs. <hi>Example,</hi> he both wrongs me, and injures himſelf. For I have ſaid nothing againſt any Conformiſts, but what I'm more capable than willing to prove; Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> has ſaid nothing againſt the Diſſenters, but what Mr. <hi>B.</hi> has made his buſineſs to diſprove. How then I can be ſaid to have copied Mr. <hi>Wrs.</hi> Example. I ſee not. In the ſubſequent Period he tells us, <hi>He ſees ſo little good from, takes ſo little delight in theſe illnatur'd Subjects, that he'l give no occaſion for new heats by examining their truth or juſtice on either one hand or the other;</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Reſolution I confeſs, in a Perſon that had not adminiſtred occaſion for new heats. But in Mr. <hi>B's.</hi> Circumſtances, 'tis as if he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Men quarelling, ſhould lay about him on both hands till he were out of breath, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little recover'd ſhou'd tell 'em, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I ſhall give no occaſion for new heats, by examining the juſtice of your quarrel on either hand. But above all paſſages in Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>I'm amaz'd</hi> at his ſummoning the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt <hi>to make reparation to the Public for the harm he has done by his unſeaſonable Reflections.</hi> If in that comprehenſive Term <hi>[Public]</hi> the Government <hi>be</hi> included, it ſurpaſſes my skill to reconcile Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to himſelf; who but a few lines, before acquits the Apologiſt of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections caſt on the Government. I could alſo tell him, from Perſons of eminent figure, and comprehenſive knowledge in public affairs (but as much Strangers to the Apologiſt as Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) the Apology is ſo far from doing harm, that it has done good ſervice to the Government. By ſuggeſting in ſome of the Queries ſeveral momentous points, which had not been done by any before in Print, and was the Intereſt of the Government and Kingdoms to be inform'd off and further inquir'd into. I cou'd ſay more of that Pamphlet were it not my own. If by (Publick) Mr. <hi>B.</hi> mean, the Subjects of theſe Kingdoms Loyally affected to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſtudious of an Union of Proteſtants, he will not find the leaſt Reflection caſt upon any one of 'em. It remains, then that by Public be underſtood the Diſaffected to the Government and Public Weal, (a fourth I cannot
<pb facs="tcp:133463:8"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> eminent Sons of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>England.</hi> I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harge therefor againſt the Apology might have been ſpar'd, as being both unkind in him, in it ſelf unjuſt, and of no ſervice to the Public. Nor can I admire the reaſon or modeſty of his inference from that groundleſs charge—<hi>i. e.</hi> that the <hi>Apologiſt make a Panegyrick on the oppoſite Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> before conviction of wrong (in an high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) done 'em, and demonſtrative evidence too of their extraordinary both merit and quality, ſuch only being the proper Objects of a Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick. But I forgive Mr. <hi>B.</hi> who no doubt expects to find his own Name in the Catalog of the <hi>Worthies of the Moderate and Sober Clergy Con and Non, whoſe Carriage</hi> (he tells us in the next period) <hi>will furniſh our two Panegyricki with materials enough.</hi> And tho I ſomewhat ſcruple to ſay with Mr. <hi>B.</hi>'s the venerable Mr, <hi>Wr.</hi> his excellent Pen; which Epithets Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf cannot think ſeriouſly beſtow'd, nor wou'd Mr. <hi>B.</hi>'s be thought to ſpeak Ironically. Yet leaſt Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſhou'd hereafter tax the Apologift with ill Humor, and that I may alſo demonſtrat my Zeal for the Union of Proteſtants, I hereby promiſe to accompliſh his wiſh, in Writing a Panegyric on my oppoſit party; that is, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> including the Head, all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants diſaffected to the preſent Government, and who have been in any former, or in the preſent Reign are obſtructers of the Union of Proteſtants and the Peace of theſe Kingdoms. Theſe only have I reflected on, theſe only are my oppoſit party; theſe will afford me plenty of Materials for a Panegyrick. Omitting therefore the firſt ſix Centuries of Chriſtianity I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with mence the ſeventh, in which <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> furniſht <hi>England</hi> with the firſt Metropolitan <hi>i. e. Auguſtin</hi> the Monk, who ſubjected the Church of <hi>England</hi> to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> being himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall'd in the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> by two of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, who by arm'd force cut off 1200 of the poor Monks of <hi>Bangor</hi> in one day, for refuſing Subjection to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to receive <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for their Arch-Biſhop. His moſt eminent Succeſſors, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm,</hi> but eſpecially St. <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Biſhops to the beginning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; I ſhall ſignalize with Characters and Elogies anſwerable to their eminent Qualities and Services to the Church and State: In the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. I ſhall omit nothing of the high Merits of Cardinal <hi>Woolſey</hi>— in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign Biſhop <hi>Bouner,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner,</hi> and others of Eternal Memory. In Queen <hi>Elizabeth's,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> who by his letters and Counſels prevail'd with Her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty reſerv'd to Herſelf, and wou'd by no means, ſubmit to the Scan of a Parliament; Such were the Reformation of Religion, the making of War and Peace, the Succeſſion to the Crown, the Queens Marriage. By which methods, ſays the Hiſtorian, the Reformation was for an intire Age obſtructed in <hi>England.</hi> Of all Biſhops I deſign the higheſt Encomiums for Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> whoſe incomparable Wiſdom, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our Church, he gave eminent Inſtances off, in the latter end of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, and fully diſplay'd in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> I. But my Rhetorical Flowers I ſhall reſerve for thoſe that Acted on our Theatre in the two laſt Reigns, and in this Reign only for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Scotland;</hi> the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> having univerſally of late given ample demonſtration of their Loyalty to their Preſent Majeſties, can therefore with no colour of Truth or Juſtice be included in the object of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd Panegyric. All this I ſhall deliver in a Stile as much ſublimer than the Apology, as it is above thoſe dreggs of ſenſe in the back-ſide Advertiſement. But before I put Pen to Paper on this Subject, I expect Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> will from the Preſs oblige himſelf to be equally generous, in Writing a Panegyric on my party; the matter whereof I will, if he require it, furniſh him with. And that the Reflector make a Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric on the Apologiſt, who in this Paper has demonſtrated the truth of the Apology, and every Period againſt it in the Reflections falſe and many of 'em Self-contradictious. I wou'd alſo hope that Mr. <hi>Boyes</hi> who has given the Precept will likewiſe give the Precedent of a Panegyric on Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> whom he has ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reflected on in <hi>page</hi> 2 and 23. which I read with Indignation; <hi>Legem ſibi dixerat ipſe.</hi> What follows in Mr. <hi>Boyes</hi> Concluſion I dare ſay, both Parties will in thoſe general Terms ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to. For my own part, I am ſo averſe to the humor and principle of thoſe who wou'd <hi>ſet the Proteſtant Religion on the narrow Pedeſtal</hi> (now I underſtand that hard word) <hi>of a Party,</hi> that I ſincerely promiſe to dedicate my little all to promote the Union of Proteſtants, Their Majeſties and the Kingdom's Intereſt. I ſhould in the laſt place encounter the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement at the end of Mr. <hi>Wrs.</hi> Vindication; this noiſom Page brings to my thoughts the great <hi>Chamier</hi> a Presbyterian Divine, <hi>Beza</hi>'s Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor (whoſe <hi>Panſtratia</hi> is not equall'd by any performance extant of any one Divine in theſe Kingdoms againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>) This great Man ſome where ſays, he us'd to viſit the Schoolmen, as Strangers do a Princes Palace; where being entertain'd with all the grateful
<pb facs="tcp:133463:8"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of this Page, and ſhall not here rob the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſer of the honour of Triumph in his refined Stile; tho' I could name men of Senſe, two or three, who have impeach'd of Nonſence, his <hi>Only that he wou'd be glad,</hi> as incoherent with the preceding words; of Battology (to paſs his tautologys) his <hi>Not worth the notice—any farther notice—</hi> and all in one Period; for the whole Page is no more. The only lines Printed on behalf of Mr. <hi>Wr.</hi> Narrative that bid at a maſculin Stile, are the Dedication. Yet, in <hi>Page</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> the laſt, <hi>but,</hi> is at beſt Impertinent: in <hi>Page</hi> 2. <hi>Could ever make them think of ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring,</hi> is mean Grammer: the Period which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>but as the whole—this ſhould then—</hi> is mean Sence: In <hi>Page</hi> 3 <hi>—but that ſince— for that becauſe more—</hi> is ſuch a ſtile as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Advertiſement you may read in <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Anim. Lib. 45. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA in this VINDICATION.</head>
            <p>IN Page 1. Column. 1. Line 15. at 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> ſhut the <hi>Parentheſis.</hi> l. 25. at <hi>Hannibal,</hi> put a <hi>Colon.</hi> Column 2. l. 8. r. <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi> p. 2. c. 1. l. 5. r. <hi>Ferſons.</hi> l. 25. for <hi>end</hi> r. <hi>could not be.</hi> p. 6. c. 1. l. 5. at <hi>Narrative</hi> add a <hi>Period.</hi> l. 45. after <hi>arriv'd</hi> inſert <hi>not.</hi> c. 2. after <hi>in</hi> inſert <hi>the.</hi> p. 7. c. 1. l. 5. after <hi>Man</hi> inſert <hi>in.</hi> c. 2. under <hi>Query</hi> 4. l. 13. r. <hi>generouſly.</hi> p. 8. under <hi>Query</hi> 6. l. 5. r. <hi>faireſt.</hi> l. 19. r. <hi>Sacramental.</hi> c. 2 l. 10. r. <hi>repreſented.</hi> p. 9. c. 1. under <hi>Query</hi> 8. l. 6. r. 50000, or 100000 <hi>Men.</hi> c. 2. under <hi>Query</hi> 9. l. 2. after <hi>paſs,</hi> write <hi>too,</hi> p. 10. c. 1. l. 33. r. <hi>Books.</hi> l. 37. after <hi>with,</hi> inſert <hi>him.</hi> c. 2. l. 26. r. <hi>Sect.</hi> p. 11. c. 1. l. 9. after <hi>of,</hi> dele <hi>the.</hi> Leſſer faults the ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will pardon, if not Correct in paſſage.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA in the APOLOGY.</head>
            <p>IN Page 2. line 16. for <hi>Ingenious</hi> read <hi>Ignominious.</hi> p. 3. l. 7. after <hi>(with)</hi> place a <hi>Colon.</hi> p. 4. after <hi>(already)</hi> put a <hi>Semicolon.</hi> p. 16. l. 8. at <hi>(any)</hi> put a <hi>Colon.</hi> l. 9. for <hi>(to)</hi> read, <hi>(do)</hi> l. 14. read <hi>quid.</hi> p. 17. l. 18. at <hi>Europ,</hi> inſert <hi>(ſo)</hi> l. 24. <hi>dele a Cypher.</hi> p. 19. l. 16. read <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</hi> p. 21. l. 2. read <hi>(ſay)</hi> p. 23. l. 28. after <hi>(only)</hi> inſert <hi>(as it.)</hi> p. 24. l. 24. dele <hi>(been)</hi> p. 25. l. 28. at <hi>(diſcomfiture)</hi> cloſe the <hi>Parentheſis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
